Finding Aid for Shirley Wohlfield Papers, 1972-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Shirley Wohlfield Papers, 1972-1988
Wohlfield, Shirley
1 linear ft., and 1 oversized volume.
88188 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan, anti-busing activist. Correspondence, speeches, minutes of meetings, and other materials relating to her involvement with anti-busing organizations, principally Northeast Mothers Alert, Mothers Alert Detroit, and the National Association for Neighborhood Schools; also files detailing involvement with Happiness of Women (HOW) and the 14th Congressional District Republican Committee; and scrapbook containing clippings and photographs relating to anti-busing rallies and activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Shirley Wohlfield (Donor No. 7493 ) in October 1987 and September 1995.
The collection is open to research.
Shirley Wohlfield first became involved in local politics when in 1973, in an effort to protect her three sons from what she viewed as the dangers of court-ordered desegregation via busing, she began organizing efforts to stop forced busing in 1973. Like many of her colleagues, Wohlfield entered this movement with little experience in political and social protest organization. Convinced of the rectitude of her position, Wohlfield organized the Northeast Mothers Alert, serving as secretary and president of Mothers Alert Detroit, which eventually affiliated with the National Association for Neighborhood Schools. This broadening of scope from neighborhood to city to nation reflects the extent to which these activists would go in order to secure local control over education. The antibusing movement peaked from 1975 to 1976 when Mothers Alert Detroit counted over two thousand members. After court decisions limited busing for desegregation to within Detroit city bounds, antibusing activism abated. Whites chose to remove their children from possible risk by moving from the city or enrolling them in private schools.
Mothers Alert Detroit did not confine its activities to anti-busing. As the busing issue subsided, Wohlfield joined protests against issues such as the Equal Rights Amendment and teaching about population control in the schools. These activities led to her involvement in related organizations such as Happiness of Womanhood, Inc. (HOW), an organization led by Patt Barbour and begun around 1973. This national group stressed the "joys of womanhood and the preservation of femininity." One of its objectives was to defeat the Equal Rights Amendment.
Involvement in MAD and HOW eventually led Wohlfield to participation in the conservative 14th Congressional District of the Michigan Republican Party. Wohlfield served as secretary for the district committee for several years and as a member of the State Republican Committee during 1981 where she represented the 14th District on the Campaign Committee.
The collection provides a telling insight into Detroit's school desegregation by forced busing. Wohlfield's committed personal involvement offers an important perspective into the antibusing movement. Her responsibilities as executive secretary and president of Mothers Alert Detroit are well documented in the minutes, correspondence, and notes in the collection. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Northeast Mothers Alert; Mothers Alert Detroit; Republican Party 14th Congressional District Committee; and Other Organizational Activities.
Subjects:
Busing for school integration--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.); Education--Michigan--Detroit.; Happiness of Women, Inc.; Mothers Alert Detroit.; National Association for Neighborhood Schools.; Northeast Mothers Alert (Detroit, Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.). 14th Congressional District Republican Committee.; Schools--Michigan--Detroit.; Wohlfield, Shirley.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Busing (School integration).; Demonstrations--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Demonstrations.; Mothers Alert Detroit.; Wohlfield, Shirley.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Northeast Mothers Alert (NEMA), 1972-1975
  The Northeast Mothers Alert series includes correspondence, some historical information about the movement, and speeches made by Wohlfield against forced busing.
  - Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - History and notes, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - SW speeches against forced busing, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- Mothers Alert Detroit (MAD), 1972-1984 (primarily 1975-1977)
  The Mothers Alert Detroit series includes minutes, correspondence, clippings, press releases, flyers for MAD rallies, and other organizational materials. Of special interest is a scrapbook, dated between 1972 and 1975, and containing photographs from rallies, marches, and fund-raisers.
  - Brief re Bradley v Milliken, 1975 (Box 1)
    (includes NEMA material)
  - Bylaws, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Executive board minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
  - General meetings minutes, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Meeting minutes and other jottings and notes, 1975-1976, 2 spiral notebooks (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973-1984 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - SW notes on MAD and NEMA, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - SW notes on sex education, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1972-1975 (Volume 1)
- Republican Party 14th Congressional District Committee, 1978-1988
  The Republican Party 14th Congressional District Committee series is arranged alphabetically and includes minutes, meeting agendas, campaign materials, legal papers and petitions forwarded to the Credentials Committee regarding disputes over the election of delegates in the 14th Congressional district and out-state for the 1983 state Republican convention.
  - Convention Agenda, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Credentials Committee, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Delegate Rosters, 1982-1988 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1981-1988 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    (includes minutes)
- Other organizational activities
  The Other Organizational Activities series documents Wohlfield's participation in Happiness of Womanhood, Inc. and the National Association for Neighborhood Schools.
  - Happiness of Womanhood, Inc. (HOW), 1973-1983 (Box 1)
  - National Association for Neighborhood Schools, 1976-1978 (Box 1)